Guide to the Marshall T. Meyer Papers, 1902-2004 and undated, bulk 1984-1993 RL.00895
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Marshall T. Meyer papers
1902-2004 and undated, bulk 1984-1993
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Meyer, Marshall T.
RL.00895
63.8 Linear Feet
Marshall T. Meyer was an activist rabbi who worked in Argentina during the period of the Dirty War/El Proceso (mid 1970s to mid 1980s). The papers of Marshall T. Meyer span the years 1919-2004. The collection contains personal and professional correspondence from throughout Meyer's career as a religious leader and human rights activist; his published and unpublished writings and speeches; printed material collected by Meyer; Meyer's working and research files organized by geography, organizations, people, and subject; personal files, including appointment books, biographical material, papers from Meyer's school days, photographs, memorabilia, and material documenting his numerous engagements; audio tapes and cassettes of Meyer's services, interviews, lectures, and other events; and Betacam and VHS videocassette recordings of interviews and other public appearances by Meyer.
Approx. 48,900 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Originals of video and audiotape are closed to use. Patrons must request use copies to access the content of the material.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Marshall T. Meyer Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2004.
Online Items
Selected materials from this collection have been digitized and are available in the Marshall T. Meyer Papers - Duke Digital Collections.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1930 Born in Brooklyn, raised in Norwich, Conn.
1952 Graduated from Dartmouth College
1958 Ordained rabbi at Rabbinical School of the Jewish Theological Seminary of America
1959 Appointed rabbi of Congregacíon Israelita in Buenos Aires, Argentina
1962 Founded Seminario Rabinico Latinoamericano in Buenos Aires
1963 Founded Comunidad Bet El in Buenos Aires, Argentina
1983 Awarded medal of San Martin by Argentine President Raul Alfonsin
1984 Appointed to National Commission on the Disappearance of Persons (CONADEP)
1984 Returned to New York City to head congregation B'nai Jeshurun
1993 Died of cancer in New York City at age 63
Rabbi Marshall T. Meyer was a progressive and activist rabbi who expounded a politically engaged Conservative Judaism. For Meyer, religion was inseparable from his politics, which spanned the breadth of local, national, and international arenas.
Meyer received his education from Dartmouth and the Jewish Theological Seminary of America, where he came under the influence of Rabbi Abraham Joshua Heschel. After being ordained rabbi in 1958, Meyer and his family moved to Buenos Aires, Argentina, in 1959, where they were to stay until 1984. During his tenure as rabbi of Comunidad Bet El, Meyer led the reinvigoration and renaissance of Argentina's Jewish community. He also lived and worked through the political upheavals and turmoil of the 1970s and 1980s, openly speaking out against the human rights abuses perpetrated under the rule of the military junta, and visiting and attempting to secure the release of prisoners ("the disappeared") in clandestine jails. Meyer was instrumental in negotiating the release of Jacobo Timerman, who later dedicated his work, Prisoner Without a Name, Cell Without a Number to Meyer. After the return of democracy to Argentina in 1983, Argentine President Raul Alfonsin recruited Meyer to serve on CONADEP (National Commission on the Disappearance of Persons), which led a national investigation to establish the extent of the abuses suffered under the military junta.
Meyer returned to the United States in 1984 and took over the helm of congregation B'nai Jeshurun, reviving the decaying New York City synagogue and transforming it into a dynamic center for Judaism in the United States. Meyer advocated for intra-religious dialogue and peace efforts, the plight of marginalized groups within the United States, human rights abuses in Central America (El Salvador, Nicaragua, and Guatemala), and for peace and respect for human rights in Israel and Palestine.
Master electronic records
Accessioned files originally stored on \cx4-fe-nas01.oit.duke.edu\TUCASI_CIFS4\rbmscl\accessions\ in two directories:
2004-0036 Meyer, Marshall 2004-336
Upon processing in 2015, completed files were rearranged and moved to \oit-nas-fe11.oit.due.edu\TUCASI_CIFS14\rbmscl\processed\RL00895_marshall_t_meyer
Collection Overview
The papers of Marshall T. Meyer span the years 1919-2004. The collection contains personal and professional correspondence from throughout Meyer's career as a religious leader and human rights activist; his published and unpublished writings and speeches; printed material collected by Meyer; Meyer's working and research files organized by geography, organizations, people, and subject; personal files, including appointment books, biographical material, papers from Meyer's school days, photographs, memorabilia, and material documenting his numerous engagements; audio tapes and cassettes of Meyer's services, interviews, lectures, and other events; and Betacam and VHS videocassette recordings of interviews and other public appearances by Meyer.
The collection contains extensive evidence of Meyer's activities and interests, especially those he engaged in during his tenure at Comunidad Bet el in Buenos Aires, Argentina, and then at B'nai Jeshurun in New York City. The files document Meyer's professional activities, including his often over-lapping roles as religious leader, scholar, and human rights activist. Much of the material in the collection reflects Meyer's devotion and commitment to a socially and politically engaged Conservative Judaism and his involvement with Jewish communities around the world. Meyer was particularly involved in calling attention to human rights violations and working with the victims of violent political oppression in South and Central America in the 1970s and 1980s and then in Palestine, Israel, and the Middle East in the 1990s. Meyer's extensive involvement and leadership in national and international religious, peace, and human rights organizations such as the World Council of Churches are also well-represented, as is his life-long association with his alma maters, Dartmouth College and the Jewish Theological Seminary of America.
The Correspondence Series contains letters in English and Spanish written and received by Meyer (additional correspondence is also contained in Meyer's research files and electronic files). Significant correspondents include Louis Finkelstein, Abraham Joshua Heschel, and Shalom Spiegel.
The Writings and Speeches Series holds Meyer's original compositions in English, Spanish, and Hebrew. These compositions include various literary genres (op-eds, newspaper articles, essays) as well as speeches, addresses, and sermons.
The Research Files Series is subdivided into four categories: Geographic, Organizations, People, and Subject. These files may contain correspondence, notes, printed material, writings, and ephemera. The most common themes that run through this series include human rights, Jewish life, rabbinic education, Latin American Jewry, the Middle East, and Argentina's "Disappeared." The Research Files Series displays a deeper level of intellectual involvement by Meyer (e.g. annotations on printed material, categorizing and filing, integration of correspondence)
The Printed Material Series includes newspapers, clippings, monographs, and serials that Meyer collected over the years. Subjects cover similar territory as the research files. Unlike the Research Files, this material is generally not annotated and was less organized.
The Teaching Material Series contains material from classes taught by Meyer.
The Personal Files Series includes material largely outside the scope of Meyer's professional work: photos, memorabilia, schoolwork, and appointment books.
Video and audio recordings of Meyer's engagements are found in the Audiovisual Material Series. These include lectures, speeches, interviews, television appearances, and religious services. Originals of video and audio tape are closed to use. Patrons must request use copies to access the content of the material.
The Condolences Series contains cards and notes expressing sympathy on Meyer's death. Many of these contain testimonials and reminiscences of his role as rabbi and activist.
Finally, the Electronic Files Series contains transcriptions of documents authored by or related to Meyer, many of which overlap with the content of and the Correspondence, Writings and Speeches, Teaching Material, and Audiovisual Materials Series.
Restorative justice -- Argentina; Judaism and social problems; Judaism -- 20th century; Conservative Judaism; Latin America -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Argentina -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Victims of state-sponsored terrorism -- Argentina; State-sponsored terrorism -- Argentina; Human Rights -- Middle East; Human Rights -- Palestine; Human Rights -- Religious aspects -- Judaism; Human Rights -- South America; Disappeared persons -- Argentina; Human Rights -- Argentina; Human Rights -- Israel; Human Rights -- Latin America; Videocassettes; Speeches; Jewish scholars; Jews -- Argentina; Human rights workers; Machine-readable records; Memorabilia; South America -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Audiocassettes; Photographs; Meyer, Marshall T.; World Council of Churches; Seminario Rabínico Latinoamericano; Dartmouth College -- Alumni and alumnae; Argentina. Comisión Nacional sobre la Desaparición de Personas; Jewish Theological Seminary of America; Human Rights Archive (Duke University)
- Correspondence Series, 1943-1994 and undated, 7 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains correspondence relating to the life and work of Marshall Meyer. The series begins with general correspondence, both personal and professional, to Meyer from many different individuals. Next, individuals and groups with whom Meyer corresponded frequently have been arranged alphabetically according to their last name. Some related materials can be found in the Electronic Files Series.
  - 1943 July 12-1985 Oct. 12 (8 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1985 Oct. 14-1987 Dec. 29 (7 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1988 Jan. 1-1990 June 14 (7 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1990 June 19-1994 Jan. 20 (7 folders) (Box 4)
  - Aguins, Marcos (Box 4)
  - Baron, Salo (Box 4)
  - B'nai Jeshurun (1 folder) (Box 4)
  - B'nai Jeshurun (6 folders) (Box 5)
  - Bud (Box 5)
  - Burman, Shoshana (Box 5)
  - Chapman, Rivy (Box 5)
  - Cohen, Gershon (Box 5)
  - Dartmouth College (Box 5)
  - Dimitrovsky (Box 5)
  - Finkelstein, Louis (Box 6)
  - Freidman, Theodore (Box 6)
  - Fuller, Margaret (Box 6)
  - Gaston-Voute, Lloyd (Box 6)
  - Gelassen, Maria (Box 6)
  - Greeting Cards (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Heschel, A.J. (Box 6)
  - Hillel, Friedman (Box 6)
  - Kalmanoff, Martin (Box 6)
  - Kelman, Wolfe (Box 6)
  - Kemper, Manuel (Box 6)
  - Lewinsky, Saverio (Box 6)
  - Meyer, Marshall (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Mirelman (Box 6)
  - Nuesner, Jacob (Box 6)
  - Perednik, Gustavo (Box 7)
  - Popell, Berte (Box 7)
  - Rita (Box 7)
  - Rosita and Enrique (Box 7)
  - Samber, Moshe (Box 7)
  - Scott-Craig, Pat (Box 7)
  - Segal, Bernard (Box 7)
  - Siegel, Seymour (Box 7)
  - Spiegel, Shalom (Box 7)
  - Spritzer, David (Box 7)
  - Swerdlow, David (Box 7)
  - Telegrams (Box 7)
  - Undated (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Weiner, Eugene (4 folders) (Box 7)
  - Wheelwright, Philip (Box 7)
  - Wiel, Adolfo (Box 7)
  - Wiesel, Elie (Box 7)
  - Wood, George C. (Box 7)
- Writings and Speeches Series, 1946-2004 and undated, 8 boxes
  Organized into the following subseries: Speeches and Writings. Folders contain copies of written and oral works produced by Meyer in English, Spanish, and Hebrew. Detailed subseries descriptions follow below.
  - Speeches Subseries, 1946-1993 and undated, 6 boxes
    Documents three types of oral addresses given by Meyer in English, Spanish, and Hebrew: first, speeches given by Meyer (these are often final drafts of addresses to various audiences: commencements, guest lectures, etc); second, transcripts of Meyer's classical music radio show, which he conducted while attending Dartmouth College between 1946-48; third, sermon notes which are rough, handwritten notes Meyer appeared to use while addressing more informal crowds, mainly religious in nature. Many of these sermon notes are for religious services conducted during the Jewish high holidays, and the majority are written in Hebrew. Speeches and sermon notes written on small notecards have been removed from boxes 8-11 and placed in smaller notecard boxes 12-13. Some related materials can be found in the Electronic Files Series.
    - 1950 Dec. 10-1989 Oct. 23 (7 folders) (Box 8)
    - 1990 Jan. 11-1993 Sept. (2 folders) (Box 8A)
    - Undated (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Radio broadcast "Great Moments in Music", 1946-1948 (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Radio broadcast, misc., undated (Box 9)
    - Sermon notes, 1959 Jan. 7-1969 Sept. 22 (4 folders) (Box 9)
    - Sermon notes, 1970 Apr. 3-1979 May 19 (9 folders) (Box 10)
    - Sermon notes, 1982 Jan. 30-1993 May 26 (4 folders) (Box 11)
    - Sermon notes, undated (3 folders) (Box 11)
    - Notecards, undated (Box 12)
    - Sermon notes notecards, 1958 Oct. 21-1981 July 31 (Box 12)
    - Sermon notes notecards, 1981 July-1984 Nov. 30 (Box 13)
    - Sermon notes notecards, undated (Box 13)
  - Writings Subseries, 1952-2004 and undated, 2 boxes
    Contains newspaper and journal articles, essays, and reflections on Meyer's experience in Argentina during the 1970s. Files also house two manuscripts that appear to be collections of written and oral works by Meyer. The 1985 manuscript appears to have been assembled by Meyer before his death, while the undated sample manuscript (often referred to as "The Big Message") was compiled posthumously. Grouped by type then arranged chronologically. Some related materials can be found in the Electronic Files Series.
    - Writings, 1952-1993 Aug. 24 (3 folders) (Box 14)
    - Writings, undated (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Manuscript, 1985 Apr. 24 (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Published material, 1959-1978 Apr. 2 (1 folder) (Box 14)
    - Published material, 1978 Aug. 26-2004 Aug. (5 folders) (Box 15)
    - Published material, undated (Box 15)
    - Sample manuscript, undated (3 folders) (Box 15)
- Research Files Series, 1902-1993 and undated, bulk 1985-1993, 33 boxes
  Organized into the following subseries: Geographic, Organizations, People, and Subject. Files contain articles, essays, correspondence, notes, mailings, and other sources of information regarding Judaism, Latin America, human rights, peace and anti-war activism, NGO's and other areas in which Meyer was heavily involved. Although the material goes as far back as 1902, the bulk of the material is from the mid 1980s to the early 1990s. Files from Meyer's offices in Buenos Aires (up to 1984) and New York City (1984-1993) are present. All subseries are arranged alphabetically by folder title. Detailed subseries descriptions follow below.
  - Geographic Subseries, 1962-1993 and undated, 8 boxes
    Contains files organized according to specific countries or regions. The bulk of the material pertains to Argentina and includes newspaper clippings, correspondence, and files related to the Dirty War/El Proceso and its aftermath. Issues and clippings from the publications Nueva Presencia and La Razón are included, as are a collection of files related to Meyer's work with the Comisión Nacional sobre la Desaparición de Personas (CONADEP). Many of the files in this series concern Jewish life, civil rights, human rights legal cases and proceedings, war and conflict, and current events. Information regarding specific judiciary cases and their relationship to Judaism and human rights is also included in several of these folders. Organized alphabetically. Some newspapers and clippings moved to Oversize Material.
    - Argentina
      - 9 Years of Transition to Democracy, undated (Box 16)
      - AAAS delegation visits Argentina, 1984 (Box 16)
      - Abuelas de Plaza de Mayo, 1984 (Box 16)
      - Anteproyecto de documento inaugural del Asociación Poder Cuidadano, 1984 (Box 16)
      - Anti-Semitism Under Military Rule 1976-1983, Juan Carlos Mercado, 1986 (Box 16)
      - Asamblea Permanente por los Derechos Humanos [APDH], 1977-1990, 6 folders (Box 16, Box 16A)
      - Centro de Estudios Legales y Sociales (CELS), 1980-1985 (Box 16A)
      - Benchoam, Esther Debora, 1979-1989 (Box 16A)
      - Comisión Interamericana de Derechos Humanos [CIDH], 1980 (Box 17)
      - Comisión Permanente en Defensa de la Educación [COPEDE], 1984 (Box 17)
      - Comisión Nacional sobre la Desaparición de Personas [CONADEP] - CUPED, 1984, 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Comisión Nacional sobre la Desaparición de Personas [CONADEP] files, 1983-1984, 3 folders (Box 17)
      - Council on Hemispheric Affairs, 1979-1980 (Box 17)
      - Cuaderno Contra la Democracia, 1984 (Box 17)
      - Delegación de Asociaciones Israelitas Argentinas [D.A.I.A], 1984, 2000 (Box 17)
      - Denuncia sobre la situación de los detenidos - desaparecidos en la Argentina, 1980 (Box 17)
      - Deutsch, Alejandro, 1984 (Box 17)
      - Draft report on Argentina, 1987 (Box 17)
      - Draft: sense of senate resolution condemning proposed pardon for Argentine "dirty warriors", 1990 (Box 17)
      - El Sionismo en la Argentina, 1975 (Box 18A)
      - Forest of the disappeared, 1990-1991 (Box 18A)
      - Federación Latinoamericana de Asociaciones de Familiares de Detenidos-Desaparecidos [FEDEFAM], 1985-1988 (Box 18A)
      - Fundación para el Estudio y Desarallo de Cooperativismo Agrario [FEDECA], 1985 (Box 18A)
      - Fundación Servicio Paz y Justicia Argentina, 1980-1990, 2 folders (Box 18A)
      - Gravier, David, 1979-1983 (Box 18A)
      - Grossman, Jacobo Issac, 1987 (Box 18A)
      - Grutzky, Eduardo, 1976-1989 (Box 18A)
      - Human rights correspondence, 1976-1989, 4 folders (Box 18A)
      - Human rights correspondence - USA government, 1983, 1990 (Box 18A)
      - Individuals disappeared, 1980-1983 (Box 18A)
      - International League for Human Rights, 1979 (Box 18B)
      - Jaroslavsky, Maximo, 1989 (Box 18B)
      - Jewish organizations in Latin America, 1963, 1986-1988 (Box 18B)
      - Kidnapped children in Argentina: methodology of restitution..., undated (Box 18B)
      - La Luz, 1960, 1969 (Box 18B)
      - La Tablada, 1991 (Box 19)
      - List of newspaper articles re: the junta trials, 1985 (Box 19)
      - Madres de Plaza de Mayo, 1986, undated (Box 19)
      - Madres de Plaza de Mayo documentary, 1983-1985 (Box 19)
      - Memorandum, Peña de Ombu meeting June 6 1979 (Box 19)
      - Memoria Historica y Social Argentina, 1987,1989 (Box 19)
      - Movimiento Judio por los Derechos Humanos [MJDH], 1983-1984 (Box 19)
      - Neuman, Benjamin, 1988 (Box 19)
      - Newspaper clippings - Argentine Jews, 1971-1992, undated (Box 19)
      - Newspaper clippings - CONADEP, 1984-1986 (Box 19)
      - Newspaper clippings - Catholic Church and Dirty War/El Proceso, 1984-1985, undated (Box 19)
      - Newspaper clippings - Dirty War/El Proceso, 1984, 1992 (Box 19)
      - Newspaper clippings, English language, 1978-1989, undated, 3 folders (Box 19)
      - Newspaper clippings - Juicios a las juntas, 1984-1985 (Box 19)
      - Newspaper clippings - Latin America, 1985 (Box 19)
      - Newspaper clippings - Meyer, Marshall, 1984-1985 (Box 19)
      - Newspaper clippings, Spanish language, 1979-1989, 1994, undated (Box 19)
      - Noe, Víctor Jacobo, 1976-1983 (Box 19)
      - Nomina de personas requeridas por sus familiares..., 1978 (Box 19)
      - Nunca Mas review, 1985-1986 (Box 19)
      - OAS - Statement of the Chairman...concerning certain charges made by the ambassador of Chile..., 1981 (Box 19)
      - Politica de gobierno de Carter sobre America Latina..., 1979 (Box 19)
      - Proyecto de orden del dia de la convencio territorial de la D.A.I.A., 1983 Oct. (Box 20)
      - Religious organizations, 1979-1989, undated (Box 20)
      - Report of the mission of lawyers to Argentina, 1979 (Box 20)
      - Report of visit to Devoto Prison April 8, 1979 (Box 20)
      - Rudnick, Issac, 1981 (Box 20)
      - Secretaria de desarollo humanos y familia-Dr. Enrique de Vedia, 1984, undated (Box 20)
      - Suarez-Mason Case, 1988 (Box 20)
      - Testimonios Sobre la Represión y la Tortura, 1984 (Box 20)
      - Timerman, Jacobo, 1978-1984, 1991, 2002, 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Tourism, undated (Box 20)
    - Brazil, 1986-1990 (Box 20)
    - Central America, 1983-1988 (Box 20)
    - Central American News, 1985-1987 (Box 21)
    - Chile, 1986-1990, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Chile - Colonia Dignidad, 1987 (Box 21)
    - Columbia, 1990 (Box 21)
    - Crisis in the Persian Gulf, 1990 (Box 21)
    - Cuba, 1985-1988, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - El Salvador, 1987-1991 and undated, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - El Salvador - Comadres, 1985-1989 (Box 21)
    - El Salvador - De la Locura a la Esperanza, 1992-1993 (Box 21)
    - Guatemala, 1985-1990 (Box 21)
    - Gulf Crisis, 1991 (Box 21)
    - Honduras, 1987-1990 (Box 21)
    - Ireland, 1992 (Box 21)
    - Ireland - Beyond Hate, 1992 (Box 21)
    - Israel, 1985-1993 and undated, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - Israel - Diaspora, 1986 (Box 22)
    - Judaism in Latin America, 1983-1985 and undated (Box 22)
    - Latin America, 1984-1986 and undated (Box 22)
    - Latin American Jewry, 1988 (Box 22)
    - Middle East, 1992-1993 (Box 22)
    - Nicaragua, 1983-1986 (Box 22)
    - Nicaragua, 1983-1989 and undated, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - Panama, 1990 (Box 23)
    - Paraguay, 1987 (Box 23)
    - Puerto Rico, 1986 (Box 23)
  - Organizations Subseries, 1902-1993 and undated, bulk 1985-1993, 22 boxes
    Contains files organized by the name of the organizations Meyer was affiliated with or had interest in. Folders include original and photocopied copies of articles, correspondence to and from organizations, notes, mailings, and conference papers and schedules. Organizations may include churches, human rights non-government organizations (NGO's), Middle East peace organizations, pro-Israeli organizations, welfare and humanitarian organizations, universities and seminaries, and academic and religious conferences. There are extensive files of material on Dartmouth and the (American) Jewish Theological Seminary, Meyer's alma maters.
    - 92d Street Y, 1986-1988 (Box 23)
    - American Committee For Israel Peace Center, 1986-1989 (Box 23)
    - American Friends of Beth Hatefutsoth, 1986-1988 (Box 23)
    - American Friends of Center for Peace in the Middle East,1987 (Box 23)
    - American-Israel Civil Liberties Coalition, 1987-1991 (Box 23)
    - American Jewish Committee, 1986-1989 (Box 23)
    - American Jewish Congress, 1986-1993 (Box 23)
    - American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee, 1987-1991, 3 folders (Box 23)
    - American Support for the Advancement of Civil Liberties in Israel, 1981-1987 (Box 23)
    - Americans for Peace Now, 1991-1992 (Box 23)
    - Americas Society, 1985-1986 (Box 23)
    - Americas Watch, 1984-1990, 1 of 5 folders (Box 23)
    - Americas Watch, 1984-1990, 2-5 of 5 folders (Box 24)
    - Amnesty International, 1988-1990 (Box 24)
    - Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith, 1986-1989 (Box 24)